Finding Aid for Haughey Family Papers 1917-1955
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Haughey Family Papers 1917-1955
Haughey Family
3 linear ft.
Wilfrid H. Haughey family of Battle Creek, Michigan; letters of Haughey to his wife and children written while he was serving as an army surgeon in France during World War I; letters of members of the family attending University of Michigan; extensive correspondence of the Haughey children written from throughout the United States and the world during World War II.
851444 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Dr. Wilfrid Haughey (donor no. 3125 ) in 1955.
The collection is open for research.
Wilfrid H. Haughey headed a large and noteworthy University of Michigan alumni family. Wilfrid Haughey received his A.B. degree at the University of Michigan then began his medical training at the University, but graduating at the Detroit Medical College. His wife Edith Cowles attended the U-M from 1902 to 1904 but left to marry and raise a family. Together they had eight children: six sons and two daughters. All eight either attended or graduated from the University of Michigan. These were Edith (1931), Esther (1934-1937), Wilfrid Jr. (1935), Phillip (1937 arch.) Clifton (1936 eng.), Charles (1943 eng.), David (1940) and Louis (1940-1943 eng.).
The father Wilfrid H. Haughey was a Battle Creek ear, nose, and throat specialist. He was also a leader within his profession serving as president and secretary of the Calhoun County Medical Society, also secretary and president of the Southern Michigan Triological Association. In addition, he served as councilor with the Michigan State Medical Society and editor of its journal. After receiving his medical training, he entered the Army Medical Reserves in 1912 and during World War I he served as Captain and Major in the military where he was in charge of the treatment of some of the first American gas casualties.
TThe collection is composed primarily of correspondence with a smaller series of miscellaneous items. The letters are of Wilfred H. Haughey to his wife and children written while he was serving as an army surgeon in France during World War I. There are also letters of Haughey family members written to their family while attending the University of Michigan and from other members of the family written while serving in World War II.
Subjects:
Battle Creek (Mich.); Physicians--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Shipping.; Ships.; University of Michigan.--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan--Students--Correspondence.; World War, 1914-1918--Medical care--France.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genre/Form:
Photographs
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series is dated 1917-1919 and 1928-1955, and consists of original letters and typescripts of letters. This series is composed mainly of personal family letters; letters of Wilfrid Haughey written to his wife and children while serving as an army surgeon in France in World War I; and letters of his children to Haughey and his wife while they were attending the University of Michigan or serving in World War II. The letters are full of information about the activities of the family members.
  - Chronological
    - 1917-1919, 1928-1943, 43 folders (Box 1)
    - 1944-1948, undated, 15 folders (Box 2)
  - Typescripts of letters
    (in binders by date or topic)
    - Clifton Francis Haughey letters entitled "The Orient; A trip to the Orient and the building of the Schooner Orient", 1937-1938 (Box 2)
    - Family letters, 1941-1942, 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - Family letters, 1943-March 28, 1955, 5 volumes (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series consists of a few unidentified photographs and a folder of clippings and other items accumulated during Wilfrid Haughey's service during World War I.
  - Photographs, 25 items (Box 3)
    (includes prints of family activities, several soldiers in uniform, and the launching of the ship, Meriwether Lewis)
  - World War I memorabilia (Box 3)